{
  "reference_number": "11934",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "It is essential to differentiate long-lived and short-lived gases (a two basket approach) in developing policies and strategies for\n\n implementation. In addition, distinguish between fossil methane and biological methane in policies."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Emissions targets could be brought forward if there is new scientific evidence of what is required for a safe climate."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but only to increase the speed of emissions reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes â€“ together with the following: to reduce cumulative emissions sufficiently to avoid dangerous climate change, the steepest\nemissions cuts to carbon dioxide must occur in the first 10 years, with possibly less steep cuts thereafter"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Reducing emissions as quickly as possible, to mitigate the worsening effects of climate change in the future. Emission reduction rate\n\nshould be the primary driver when setting budgets. This should not be watered down because of justifications like 'economic factors',\nThe reality is there will be no economy either in NZ or worldwide, without dramatic action now to reduce emissions and minimise\neffects as much as possible."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate change is the biggest threat to human survival and wellbeing and must be the primary consideration in all government and\n\neconomic decision-making. It is critical that the provisions in this bill are as strong as possible, and we must not allow the primacy of\nthis issue to be diluted by the greed,lobbying and shortsightedness of industries that are already denigrating natural capital,\nparticularly fossil-fuel companies and industrial dairying. As an aunt, I want Aotearoa New Zealand - and the earth - to have a safe\n\nclimate future for my niece and nephew (aged 8 and 10) to grow up in . I do not want them growing up to an adulthood of fear,\nclimate refugees, resource wars and ultimate social collapse.. This is our last chance to take meaningful action on climate change\n\nand reverse previous governments' weak and toothless excuses for action. As figures at the UN have said, \"We are the first\ngeneration to feel the effects of climate change, and the last to be able to do something about it\". I urge the Government to take as\n\nstrong a course of action as possible, and to make the targets and frameworks in the Zero Carbon Act as stringent and ambitious as\npossible. Climate change is the main issue I vote on. I have supported formation of this government to take the ambitious action\n\nneeded. I urge them to stand strong, to defend the strong provisions set out in the discussion document, and to be courageous.\nPlease."
    }
  ]
}
